So many devs are using coding assistants
now, but they don't even know how tools
work. So, let's talk about how tools
work and how you can make the most of
them. Giving the LLM tools is done via
the system prompt. The system prompt is
just another message in the message
history which describes the LM what it's
supposed to be doing and in this case,
what tools it can call. If we zoom into
write file here, this is a tool which
writes a file to the file system and it
has two input parameters, a path which
is a string and content which is also a
string. So we're providing three things
per tool really. The name of the tool
here, write file, a description of the
tool and the parameters that it takes
and the types of those parameters. These
are specified in JSON schema. So we can
pass anything that JSON schema supports
like objects and arrays and things.
These then get injected into the system
prompt and any other info that you've
provided to the system prompt just goes
below it. So there's nothing
particularly fancy here going on. It's
just tool definitions inside the system
prompt. The magic happens when we ask
the LLM to choose a tool. We've got our
system prompt up here saying you have
access to the following tools. And then
we add a user message which says write a
new file called git ignore. We then
receive back an assistant message with a
tool call inside. This is just an
instruction from the LLM which tool to
call. It's got an ID on it and it's also
got the required parameters. In other
words, here it's writing an empty file
to the path getit ignore. Now this tool
call is just an instruction for which
tool should be called. Nothing has
happened yet. The assistant has just
produced a message. That's it. The tool
then needs to be executed on our
machine. So the LLM's created this
message. We then need to actually
execute the creation of the file on our
machine. This means that for every
single tool in the system prompt, we're
going to have functions in our codebase
that match up to those. If that's
successful, we're then going to send
back a user message to the LLM. It's
going to have the same ID as the
previous tool call, and we're going to
send it a message saying what happened
when we executed the tool. This, by the
way, is really important. If there are
any errors when the tool is executed,
then we need to show that error message
to the LLM so that it can do something
differently. So, a tool result could be
a success or it could be a failure.
Let's go one more time through the
entire flow just so you get it in your
head. We specify the tool in the system
prompt saying you have access to the
following tools, passing it a bunch of
JSON schema. We then send it a user
message saying write a new file called
get ignore. Note that we don't have to
specifically say call this tool. The LLM
itself decides which tool to call. It
then produces this tool call message
with all the right stuff inside. We then
see this tool call message and we
execute it on our machine. We then send
the result back with a message saying
what happened and then the LLM will see
this entire history and just respond
with a summary. In this case, it said
done and what should go in there. So
that's what tools are. They're just ways
of getting LLMs to produce certain types
of messages which you can then intercept
and execute on your machine and give
those results back to the LLM. And with
that simple loop, you can build really,
really powerful